Finding Aid for Dept. of Mechanical Engineering and Applied Mechanics (University of Michigan) publications, 1908-2002
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Dept. of Mechanical Engineering and Applied Mechanics (University of Michigan) publications 1908-2002, 1968-2000
University of Michigan. Dept. of Mechanical Engineering and Applied Mechanics.
1.5 linear feet
9728; Bimu; C146; 2
Teaching and research unit of the College of Engineering of the University of Michigan. Contains publications produced by or for the department, including annual reports, bibliographies, brochures and pamphlets, bulletins describing graduate programs, directories, histories, manuals, and newsletters.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The publications are received periodically from the unit (donor no. 8391 ).
The publications are open for research.
The Department of Mechanical Engineering and Applied Mechanics is a teaching and research unit of the College of Engineering of the University of Michigan.
The Department of Mechanical Engineering and Applied Mechanics Publications are divided into three series: Unit Publications, Sub-Unit Publications, and Student Publications. The bulk of the publications document the teaching and research functions of the Department of Mechanical Engineering and Applied Mechanics.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Dept. of Mechanical Engineering & Applied Mechanics.; University of Michigan--Alumni and alumnae.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Mechanical Engineering.; MEAM alumnus.; Mechanica.; 125 years of mechanical engineering at the University of Michigan.
Genre Terms:
Annual reports.; Bibliographies.; Pamphlets.; Bulletins.; Directories.; Manuals.; Newsletters.; Histories.; Reports.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Mechanical Engineering.
- Unit Publications
  The Unit Publications series contains printed material published specifically by the Department of Mechanical Engineering and Applied Mechanics. These publications are defined as being widely distributed and may be published at regular intervals. They are arranged by genre of the publication.
  The Unit Publications series contains annual reports, bibliographies, brochures, bulletins, directories, flyers, histories, lectures, manuals, newsletters, posters, programs, and reports. The annual reports document the department from 1984 to 2000. They also include the 1992-1993 annual report entitled 125 Years of Mechanical Engineering at the University of Michigan which was written to celebrate the 125th anniversary of the department. This series also includes bulletins dating from 1966 to 1995 describing the various graduate programs within the department. Under "Directories" the researcher will find faculty and staff directories from 1992 to 1997 and directories for women and minority students from the period 1992 to 1994. There is also a directory of the various manufacturing laboratories within the department. Of the two histories included in this series, the first was compiled to celebrate the centennial of the College of Engineering in 1954 and contains a brief history of the Department of Mechanical Engineering and Applied Mechanics. The centennial history of the department– Mechanical Engineering at Michigan, 1868-1968: A Volume Issued on the Occasion of the Centennial Celebration of the Department of Mechanical Engineering will also be found in this series.
  A copy of the lecture "Kansei" Engineering: The Art of Automotive Development at Mazda which was given by Kenichi Yamamoto in 1986 is included in the Unit Publications. There are three manuals contained in this series, including The Graduate Programs Handbook published in 1997 to aid the department's incoming graduate students with admission information, degree requirements, course and facility descriptions, and faculty information. There is also a 1908 manual of Drawing Standards and Conventions. The internal department Newsletter documents the activities of the faculty and staff from 1979 to 1995 with the exception of 1980.
  - Annual Reports
    - Annual Report for the Department of Mechanical Engineering and Applied Mechanics, 1981/82-1987/88, 1991/92, 1993/94-2001/02, 8 folders (Box 1)
    - 125 Years of Mechanical Engineering at the University of Michigan, 1992-1993 (2 copies) (Box 1)
    - Biennial Report, 1988-1990 (Box 1)
  - Bibliographies
    - Manufacturing Laboratories in the Department of Mechanical Engineering and Applied Mechanics, 1989 (Box 1)
  - Brochures
    - Automotive, 1959-1963 (Box 1)
    - Degree Requirements undated (Box 1)
    - Mechanical Engineering, 1956-1993 (Box 1)
    - Seminars, Colloquia, and Lectures sponsored by the department 1967-1993 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Bulletins
    - Graduate Programs in Mechanical Engineering, 1966-1991 (Box 1)
    - Graduate Programs in Mechanical Engineering and Applied Mechanics, 1993-1995 (Box 1)
    - Research Bulletin, 1992-1993, undated (Box 1)
  - Directories
    - Directory of Women and Minority Students, 1992-1994 (Box 1)
    - External Advisory Board [1995 ?] (Box 1)
    - Faculty and Staff Directory, [1992/1993]-1998, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Faculty Research Interests, 1998-1999, 2001 (Box 1)
    - Manufacturing Laboratories, [1989] (Box 1)
  - Flyers
    - 1992-1993 (Box 1)
  - Histories
    - A Century of Engineering Education: Department of Mechanical Engineering and Applied Mechanics, 1954 (Box 1)
    - Mechanical Engineering at Michigan, 1868-1968, [1968] (Box 1)
  - Lectures
    - "Kansei" Engineering: The Art of Automotive Development at Mazda by Kenichi Yamamoto, 1986 (Box 1)
  - Manuals
    - Drawing Standards and Conventions, 1908 (Box 1)
    - Graduate Programs Handbook, 1997-1998 [1997] (Box 1)
    - Motion and Time Study Notes for Mechanical Engineering Course M.E. 136, 1949 (Box 1)
  - Newsletters
    - Newsletter
      - 1979, 1981-1991, 12 folders (Box 1)
      - 1992-1994, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Posters
    - Laser Science and Engineering Lecture, 1999 (Box 2)
    - Sunrunner at the World Solar Challenge, 1990 undated (Box 2)
  - Programs
    - Graduate Student Symposium
      - Book of Abstracts (Box 2)
    - MEAM Spring Awards Celebration, 1997-1998 (Box 2)
    - National Science Foundation Conference 1987 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Reports
    - Fundamental Research in Manufacturing for National Competitiveness, 1992 (Box 2)
    - A Real-Time Implementation of a Robot Tool Management System With a Robot Hand Database for Flexible Assembly Cells by Paul G. Ranky, 1986 (Box 2)
    - Report of Committee on Tractive Resistance and Allied Problems by Walter E. Lay, 1939 (Box 2)
    - A Study of the Relation of Combustion to the Emissions of Atmospheric Contaminants, 1964 (Box 2)
  - Texts
    - Notes and Problems in Statics, 1946 (Box 2)
- Sub-Unit Publications
  The Sub-Unit Publications series includes brochures from the Academic Counseling Office. The Bentley Historical Library has a complete run, dating from 1992 to 2000, of the newsletters entitled The MEAM Alumnus and Mechanica from Alumni and Development. These newsletters document the activities of the faculty, staff, students, and alumni of the department. There are also publications from the Automotive Laboratory, the Center for Dimensional Measurement and Control in Manufacturing, the Fluid Dynamics Laboratory, and the Senior Design Exposition.
  - Academic Counseling Office
    - Brochures
      - Applied Mechanics, 1993 (Box 2)
      - M.S.E. Degree, 1992 (Box 2)
      - The Ph.D. Degree, 1991-1993 includes Qualifying and Preliminary Exams (Box 2)
  - Alumni and Development
    - Newsletters
      - The MEAM Alumnus [precedes Mechanica], 1992-1993 (Box 2)
      - Mechanica, 1994-2001, 8 folders (Box 2)
  - Automotive Laboratory
    - Reports 1952, 1955 (Box 2)
  - Center for Dimensional Measurement and Control in Manufacturing
    - Newsletters
      - The Coordinator, 1993 (Box 2)
  - Design Engineering Computer Aids Laboratory Texts
    - Users Guide to DRAM (Dynamic Response of Articulated Machinery), 1974 (Box 2)
  - Fluid Dynamics Laboratory
    - Reports
      - Heat Transfer In Rarefied Gases: A Survey by George S. Springer, 1969 (Box 2)
  - Senior Design Exposition
    - Flyers 1995 (Box 2)
    - Programs 1995-1996 (Box 2)
  - S. M. Wu Manufacturing Research Laboratory
    - Reports
      - Annual Report, 1993 (Box 2)
- Student Publications
  - Pi Tau Sigma
    - Brochures and Newsletters 1949, undated (Box 2)